We don't have a health insurance policy when
we need it, that is,
during hospitalization, so that we can get money. Can it ever happen
that after a hospital claim, the
next year during renewal, the
health insurance company can tell you that
you have claimed a lot of money and
we will not renew it or we will
renew it but will charge a much higher
premium? If this happens, what should you
do? Is there a way to
save yourself from such things? Watch
this video in full to know what to do if you have such a problem.
This has been discussed in detail here.  The incident began with
a post by Lincoln a week or two ago.  The
post was made by Mr. Prashant
Matre, who is the All India President of the General Insurance
Agents Association of India.  In
Mr. Mater's
post, he wrote that there are several
insurance companies that
offer health insurance.  For example, ICICI
Bank, SBI General Zoom have
included a clause in some of their policies.
The name of the change clause is the material change clause.
According to this clause, if a person's physical
condition changes and the insurance
company thinks that it can change
their renewal or
premium due to that change in physical condition, then the
insurance company can do so.
Mr. Mather's statement was that
if an insurance company thinks that a person will not renew
his policy after he gets sick and makes a claim during the
renewal period
or
charges a lot of premium, then that person will be in great
danger. As soon as this post came out, several other
companies circulated this post and
added the names of many more companies,
and a real
uproar started on social media. How can an insurance company make
such purchases outside the rules set by our insurance regulator, the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDI), which is against the customer?
When there is a real uproar on social media, the
two policies
against which this allegation was made by ICICI Lumber Company, one of which is
called
Health Advantage, the other is called Elevate and the policy
wordings of Health Advantage, which
depend on the contract on which the
policy is issued, are based on the policy
wordings.  The specific parts that were
controversial were revealed
and their position was clarified through a circular
that there is
no such condition or clause in ICICI Life
through which the customers can be free from such dangers.
Let us see the incident from the beginning.
What did Mr. Math write in the post and
what did he write in response to it? IC number is their
policy warning. We will show the screenshot here. In
the post, he writes Consumer Finding Highlight Concern Material Change
Present Save Retail Health Policy
Aim
Advantage SBI General Insurance Arogya Supreme
Super Help End June
General Insurance
Policy Holder Atify Any Material Change
Soul Condition Insir
Premium You
Modify Restrict Coverage
Limitation. That
is, as we were saying at the beginning,
if there is any such incident that the customer has a major
change in his body due to illness or
a serious illness, then the company will
increase his policy premium with everything.  If you can
ask if there is a material
change, now we will see what ICICI
Lombard has written in the circular they have issued,
material change
in our health policy, read together
fully customer friend,
primary exception,
detail
program like check, supplementary
medical, increase in
summer edition of new member
edition of optional cover, then
a very important ice number, no
rejected material change, change
policy holder premium, favorite
new condition, offer policies, we are
fully compliant with IRDI regulations and our
policy term follows standard
industry practice, that is, ICICI
Lombard claims that this clause should be
read with their renewal clause and if the two are
read together, then it will be seen that the thing is
not at all right and no
customer's claim has ever been rejected by ICICI on this
basis, if there was any disease before that and
ICSC is this Rombert  The
customer's health condition will
not change during renewal unless the sum insured is increased
or a new member is added, etc.,
and ICICI Lombard's statement is that the
policy wordings they have are
completely consistent with the IRDAI rules
and there is no
room for any inconvenience.  Let's
see what exactly is written on the ICS Lom's
claim, the renewal cross and the
material case.
First, let's come to the renewal. You can
see on the screen the renewal of policy,
it is also written in Roman numerals. Renewal not
BD on ground
person
in the preceding policy renewal will
never be denied because the claim has been made before.
Clause number seven states that for
individual products loading is on the basis of the actual
premiums in the
portfolio and not based on any
individual policy plane experience.
What does the term loading mean?  Loading
is when you take out a policy and
an extra premium may be charged on top of the standard premium,
depending on your physical condition.
If you take any medicine regularly and the company
thinks that
you should take an extra premium from the
company for having the disease for which you are also taking the medicine.  We will load that thing.
So, in the
case of renewal of ICIC number, it is written that when
you are taking a policy from the first company, a
new policy or a portfolio, when
you are entering the company for the first time, the
loading given at that time at the portfolio level
means that that loading will
never be increased in the future, meaning that
this loading will be increased later according to what claims you have made or have been made.
Such a thing will never happen. Clause
number number is safe. Number five
says no fresh underwriting
stage or no change in sum insured in the offer
letter, that is, your sum is known as
10 lakhs, 15 lakhs, 20 lakhs, if you do
not want to increase it later, then
no new underwriting will be done on you.
Underwriting means fresh evaluation of your
medical condition. When you are writing,
your medical condition will be evaluated once
and later if you ever
want to increase the sum insured, extra base sum insured,
then it can be evaluated again,
but if you want to increase the sum insured after a year, then  You are only renewing the policy for the year,
increasing the sum insured or in that case,
but you will not have any evaluation. This
increase in the sum insured will
not be rolled over with the bonus. Bonus increase does not mean
increase in the sum insured. And here it is also written in clause
seven, sub clause five,
provident
profile company
removes the loading point of one.
Suppose when you are writing the policy for the first time or
doing it, you have a cholesterol problem.
Later, you have
controlled your cholesterol level through exercise
and you need to take your cholesterol medicine.
You
told the company that now
if the company has any loading on you for having cholesterol,
then when you tell that I am
now cholesterol free and I do
not have to take medicine, then if the company thinks so, it can
remove your loading according to clause seven, sub clause five. Now let's
read the material change clause that we talk about so much. What is written there? You can see on the screen
what is called material change clause. Is there
this written there?
Screenshot but IC policy warning from
there it is
said page number number change person notify
company in writing of met change relationship decision
prop
medical examination report at each
renewal and the company may adjust the
scope of the cover and or premium if necessary according to that i.e.
suppose when I took the policy
or when someone took the policy he did not have
any disease in his body later it was found that at some point
his blood pressure or blood
sugar developed
material change cos it says that if
something like that happens then before the next renewal
the company has to inform you in writing
that your blood pressure or blood sugar has
developed that.  The doctor has detected it
and has prescribed you medicine.   There is a
debate about whether this is written according to the Material Change College after you report it, and that the company can then make
changes to your policy if it deems fit.  But the
misconception that this material change disclosure is
creating when we
read it with the renewal of policy cause, which is
mentioned in the IC Lombard circular
that the two should be read together, then it is
seen that even if there is a material change, it will
not have any effect at the time of subsequent renewal. So at least
we can say that the debate that
started with Mr. March's post that
clients can be in great danger if they give their renewal time later.  In the
event of a major illness, the company
can increase the premium significantly.  At least
I read the wording of this policy ticket of ICI Nobird
according to the wording of the Elevate policy and
according to the circular of ICI Nobird, there is
no evidence that the
company can later
put you in difficulty by increasing the premium.  Now
the question is, several more companies have
been named and what are the policies of those companies?   Is
there any such clause through which we
can understand that if the machine changes, the
company will
not increase the premium significantly or will
not allow renewal at the time of renewal, so
we need to see their policy wordings. The
main purpose of doing what I discussed in today's video is that it is
definitely necessary to review your policy,
especially those who are online or
banking,
who can review their policy. Be
sure to contact a trusted advisor to see if there is
any such clause
or there may be many other small clauses
that can cause a lot of problems during the claim if you do not understand this. Even a very
small
thing can be a problem. If it is a normal claim, it will
pass, but if there is a little
complexity, then it
can get stuck and if it is a
claim of a large amount, you will face a lot of difficulties.
So try to find out
all the pros and cons from a trusted advisor when taking your policy.
If you like the video, please share it with your friends
or those you know.  Do
n't forget to subscribe and share.  If you
encourage me, I can come up with more good videos for
you.  Greetings.